快点
Come on!
这边走
This way!
走啊 快点
Come on, quickly!
快走 快走
Move! Move!
不
No!
别挡路 滚开
Out of the way! Move!
恶鬼上身 恶鬼…
Evil inside. Evil...
走开
Vai!
- 给我亲一下 - 你去刮胡子 我才亲
- Give us a kiss, then. - You shave, I kiss.
你跟他谈过了？
You talk to him?
我答应了就一定会去
I said I would, and I will.
我们不能永远待在这儿
We cannot stay here forever.
这可不行
It's not right.
- 这里是死亡之屋 - 我知道
- This place is a house of death. - I know.
如果我们在这儿生了孩子怎么办？天怒人怨的 会生出个妖怪的
What if we make a baby here? Gods forbid. It would be a monster.
我说过我会跟他谈的
I said I'd talk to him.
嘿 好兄弟 今天是出门的好天气啊
How are you, brother? Good day out?
也许适合去郊外走走
Good day for a walk in the country maybe?
不去
No.
春天来了 百花盛开
Spring's here, blossom on the trees,
牧场上还有羊群
lambs in the meadows.
兄弟 已经一个月了
Brother, the full moon has come and gone.
也许是时候刮胡子了 (守丧时忌剃毛发)
Maybe it's time to cut off these mourning beards?
必须继续活下去
Life must continue.
你是对的
You're right.
- 你们应该走了 - 把你就这么扔下？
- You should go. - And leave you here like this?
- 那我还算得上朋友吗？- 我已经不需要朋友了
- Good friend I'd be. - I'm past need of friends.
这又是什么意思？你打算干什么？
Now what's that mean? What are you going to do?
你总不能这么一辈子傻坐下去
You can't sit here the rest of your life.
我害死了我妻子
I've caused the death of my wife.
我害死自己的孩子
I've caused the death of my children.
我害死了恺撒
I have caused the death of Caesar.
你现在还想要我做什么？
What would you have me do now?
做什么？卖肉吗？
What? Run a butcher's shop?
好啊 好啊 算我说错了
Fine, fine. Sorry I spoke.
吃你的烂粥去
Eat your damn porridge.
她是怎么样的女人？
What sort of woman is she?
- 谁？- 那个埃及女人
- Who? - The Egyptian girl.
哦 她呀 我都没怎么见过她
Oh, her. I barely met her.
一个瘦小的家伙 话很多
Skinny thing. Talks too much.
但是她总有什么特别的地方
Well, she must have something
才能诱惑凯撒这样冷若冰霜的人
to lure a cold fish like Caesar.
她是皇后
She's a queen.
如果美杜莎戴上皇冠 凯撒也照干不误
Caesar would've fucked Medusa if she'd worn a crown.
你嫉妒了 小花？
You jealous, flower?
当然 我不介意你的那些贱女人
Of course. I don't mind your whores,
但是我不希望你跟那种女人上床
but I don't want you making love to her sort.
是说所有比你更年轻 地位又高过…
Meaning younger women of higher rank than...
你的女人
you?
这条规矩倒是不错
That's a good general rule.
我会记住的
I shall remember it.
我爱你
I love you.
安东尼？
Antony?
借过说句话
A word, if I may.
什么事 可爱的孩子？
What is it, dear boy?
关于我的钱…凯撒的钱
About my money, Caesar's money.
你跟我保证过我现在可以拿到钱了
You assured me I'd have it by now.
我很抱歉 我一定是忘了 我会查看一下的
I'm so sorry. It slipped my mind. I will see to it.
好的 只不过你已经说了好几次了
Good, only that is what you've said several times now.
咳 这种事情总是很花时间的
Well, these things take time.
我们谈的可是一大笔钱
We are talking vast sums of money.
一大堆的文书和法律上的事要处理
There's a great deal of paperwork and lawyering to be done and...
那什么时候钱才能转到我手上
So when can I expect transfer to my control?
干吗这么急？
What's the rush?
哪个恶婆娘女人给你施压了？
Some wicked woman giving you the squeeze?
别担心 我会留意的
Don't worry. I'll see to it.
旅途平安吧？
Tolerable voyage?
- 是的 - 我自己…
- It was. - Myself...
我受不了船
I cannot abide ships and boats.
简直像是在笼子里 不是吗？
Too much like cages, ne?
外加可能淹死的危险
With the added risk of drowning.
你跟我们上次见面时不一样了
You've changed since we last met.
我以前见过你吗？
Have I seen you before?
是的
Yes.
在亚历山大港 跟凯撒一起
In Alexandria, with Caesar.
因为你们穿的制服 你们看上去都差不多
It's those uniforms you wear. You all look alike.
那个时候我看你 你显得更…
When I saw you then, you seemed...
开心
happier.
出什么事了吗？
Is something wrong?
这问题问得真奇怪 凯撒已经死了
A strange question. Caesar is dead.
他曾经如同我的丈夫一样
He was as a husband to me.
我对他来说也如同妻子
I was as a wife to him.
- 我让你发笑了 - 请原谅
- I amuse you. - Forgive me.
这是个奇怪的想法
It's an odd thought.
一名罗马执政官有个埃及老婆
A Roman consul with a 'Gyptian wife.
- 这是不可能的 你明白吗？- 我看不出来
- Wouldn't do, you know? - I fail to see why.
我想我们该开始谈判了
I believe we may begin negotiations.
这是我们提案的文本
Here is the text of our proposal.
我们将把它加入参议院的纪录
We would read it into the Senate record.
我 马克·安东尼 作为罗马执政官
"I Mark Antony, Consul of Rome,
保证我们的军队会继续
"guarantee that our armies will continue
保卫克莉奥佩特拉的皇位
"to protect and preserve the throne of Cleopatra,
即托勒密的子嗣 埃及的皇后
"child of Ptolemy, Queen of Egypt,
莎草与蜂蜜的女主人 如此这般 这般如此
"mistress of sedge and bee, et cetera."
- 你开出的价格是多少？- 女王陛下将保证
- What is your price? - Her majesty will guarantee
每月送上10船标准等级的谷物
10 grain shipments a month at the standard rate,
从国家税收中 执政官将获得一份个人名义的馈赠
from which revenues the Consul will accept as a personal gift
每月48000德那留斯银币
48,000 denarii a month.
- 35 - 45
42 每个月第一天交付
42, delivered on the kalends.
我们就这么说定了？
Are we done, then?
还有一件事
One more thing.
我和凯撒的孩子已经快四岁了
My son by Caesar is near four years old.
他已经开始询问关于他父亲的事了
He has begun to ask questions about his father.
真温馨
How touching.
他现在还太小 不明白事理
He's too young to understand now,
不过很快我就不得不告诉他
but soon I must tell him
他父亲的臣民不接受他
that his father's people do not accept him.
不当他是合法的儿子
Not as a true legal son.
绝对不可能 人民不会喜欢这种事
It will never happen. The people wouldn't like it.
我们没有政治意图
We have no political design,
只不过想让我孩子开心一点
merely the happiness of my boy.
简单地公布一下
A simple public declaration
父子关系就足够了
of paternity will suffice.
那我又能从中得到什么好处？
And what would I profit by that?
你将得到我永远的感谢
You would have my eternal gratitude.
答应我…
Promise me...
那也不是不可能
That's possible.
宣布我的儿子是凯撒合法的子嗣
Declare my boy a lawful son of Caesar,
我们就可以成为朋友
then we shall be friends.
- 你不相信我？- 不那么相信
- You don't trust me? - Not so much.
你看上去十分善变
You have a changeable look about you.
你看错了
You're mistaken.
我就像农神的祭司一样坚定
Steady as a priest of Saturn, me.
过来
Come now.
法律禁止触碰女王陛下
It is not permitted to touch.
真有礼貌啊
Nice manners...
对一个妓女来说
for a whore.
如果一定要我献出自己
If I must prostitute myself
来换取我的国家和家族的利益
for the good of my country and my family,
我会的
I will.
但是客人得先把肉钱付了 他做到了吗？
But the customer pays first, does he not?
让你儿子去吃屎吃到死
Your son will eat shit and die
我再宣布他合法
before I make him legal.
看见了没有？
You see?
非常善变
Very changeable.
很遗憾我们不能达成共识
Sorry we couldn't agree.
也许你会改变主意
Perhaps you'll change your mind.
明天的晚宴上见 我相信
We'll see you at dinner tomorrow, I believe.
尽管他不是太阳神
He wasn't Apollo, by no means,
至少伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼还活着的时候
but when Erastes Fulmen was alive
艾文台山上可是一切太平
there was peace on the Aventine.
现在城里的所有黑帮 都为了争夺山上的控制权打成一团
Now every gang in the city's fighting for control of the hill.
每一天街上都充斥着暴力 每一日都是杀声震天
Every day there's violence, every day there's...
呼 哈
hoo-ha.
- 这会断送贸易 - 我会料理的
- It's killing commerce. - I will see to it.
难道贸易不是公民道德的根基么？
And is not commerce the root of civic virtue?
如果贸易被扼杀 罗马难道还能…
Can Rome long survive if commerce is...
你可以走了
You may go.
必须…
Something...
必须对艾文台山采取措施
Something must be done on the Aventine.
是的 是的 我知道了 我满耳朵灌的都是这种事
Yes, yes, I know. I hear of nothing else.
黑帮不会停止他们之间的战争
The gangs will not stop fighting of their own accord.
不管最后谁控制了艾文台 这个代价都太大了
It is too rich a prize. Whoever controls the Aventine
控制港口和粮食供应
controls the docks and the grain supply...
- 我都知道 - 暴力还会蔓延
- I am aware! - The violence will spread.
如果不加制止 整个城市都会很快
If it is not stopped, the whole city will swift descend
陷入一片混乱和饥荒 我恐怕你会为此受到指责
into chaos and famine and you will be blamed, I'm afraid.
尽管这不是你的错 可还是…
Though it'd be none of your fault, of course. Still...
我会处理的
I will handle it.
现在
Now...
你找我有什么事？
what can I do for you?
- 是你找我来的 - 哦 是的 关于那件事
- You sent for me. - Oh, yes, that.
给他看看
Show him.
简直就是城里所有流氓地痞的名录
It appears to be a list of every dishonest rascal in the city.
真滑稽
Very droll.
这是名单选举的候选人名单
It is a list of candidates for next year's elections
是我们敬爱的凯撒去世前写好的
drawn up by our beloved Caesar just before he was taken from us.
伯斯卡在他的文件堆里找到的
Posca found it amongst his papers.
喔 幸运的大发现啊 你还真是不可思议啊 伯斯卡
Another lucky find? You are prodigious, Posca.
我需要你认可这份名单
I want your endorsement of the names.
出于团结与友好的名义 诸如此类
For the sake of unity and amity, et cetera, et cetera.
这是不是有点太无耻了？
Isn't that being just a little too brazen?
谁会相信凯撒能挑这种卑鄙小人出来
Who would believe that Caesar chose such wretches?
你总不会认为这些人出钱贿赂我 好把名字加到单子上吧？
Surely you don't think those men paid me to put their names on the list?
当然不
Not at all.
我认为他们贿赂了伯斯卡
I expect they have paid Posca.
- 那么 还有什么问题？- 我的背书会变得一钱不值
- So, what's the problem? - My endorsement will be worthless.
人们会认为我是被你胁迫的
People will merely assume I've been intimidated by you.
- 难道你不是被胁迫吗？- 不完全是
- Are you not intimidated? - Not especially.
现在你还不敢杀我
At present, you cannot afford to kill me.
你需要我来管理元老院
You need me to run the Senate.
今天 我需要你
Today, I need you.
- 到了明天… - 到了明天我再担心吧
- Tomorrow... - Then tomorrow I will worry.
今天 我建议你让我把这名单上 最卑劣的无赖剔除掉
Today, I suggest you let me strike the worst scoundrels off this list.
然后我才会签字
Then I will endorse it.
很好 很好 随你喜欢吧
Fine, fine. Do as you like.
乐意效劳
A pleasure as always.
接下来 有一个委托
Next there is a delegation...
不 够了 够多了 叫我的卫兵来
No, enough. Enough of this. Call my guard.
马上就去 你走之前
Immediately. Before you go,
是不是可以谈一下我的补偿和委任的事？
if I might raise the matter of my recompense and commission?
不 不 不行 你这肮脏的希腊窃贼
No! No, you might not, you wretched Greek thief!
钱 钱 钱
Money, money, money.
我都快被财迷包围了
I'm surrounded by money-grubbers.
马克·安东尼长官 是我啊
Mark Antony, sir! It's me, sir!
第13军团的泰特斯·波罗
Titus Pullo of the 13th!
士兵波罗？
Legionary Pullo?
等一下 让他过来
Hold it. Let him through.
阁下
Sir!
你在这儿干什么？
What are you doing here?
替卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯祈求建议与忠告 长官
Requiring advice and counsel regarding Lucius Vorenus, sir.
继续说
Go on.
他已经迷糊了 长官
He has gone awry, sir.
我不知道该替他做什么
I don't know what's to be done with him.
乌瑞纳斯 长官来了
Vorenus! Officers afoot!
百夫长乌瑞纳斯
Centurion Vorenus.
- 曾经是 - 阁下？
- As was. - Sir?
看你这个死样子
Look at the fucking state of you.
- 这是丧服 长官 - 丧服？
- It's mourning dress, sir... - Mourning?
你当然该哀悼
You may well mourn.
恺撒都已经死了
Caesar is dead,
就跟你亲手下的刀子一样
and it was you as good as held the knife.
我说话的时候你他妈的给我立正站好
Stand to fucking attention when I'm talking to you!
你知不知道你的名誉已经被永远地玷污了？
You know that your name is disgraced forever?
我知道 长官
I do, sir.
“我知道 长官”
"I do, sir."
那你干吗还活着？
Why, then, are you still alive?
你怎么不去尽忠
Why have you not done your damn duty
把肚子剖开
and opened your stomach?
我比谁都想那么做 长官
I would like that above all things, sir.
但是冥神掌管了我的一切
But Dis is my master,
他会在适当的时候取走我的性命
and he will take me when he chooses.
现在 他希望我留在世上受折磨
At present, he wishes me to suffer here on this earth.
你错了 百夫长
You are wrong, Centurion.
冥神不是你的主人
Dis is not your master.
我才是
I am your master.
遵照第13军团
By sacred oath under the standards
神圣的誓言和军规
of the 13th.
长官
Sir.
还有这个 我收下了 他曾是伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼
And this, I take it, was Erastes Fulmen.
我告诉过他把这个扔掉
I told him to get rid,
可看着这东西能让他平静下来
but it calms him to look at the thing.
还不肯让这位教父死去
Not content to let our great father die,
你在艾文台山上挑起了一场战争
you start a damn war on the Aventine
几乎要毁掉整个城市
that threatens to engulf the whole fucking city.
现在
Now...
想不想赎罪 百夫长？
would you like a chance to redeem yourself, Centurion?
无法赎罪的
There's no redemption.
没有谁是不能赎罪的 卢西尔斯
No man is beyond redemption, Lucius.
连你也不例外
Not even you.
然后呢？
And so?
然后什么？
那个埃及女人 老实交待
The Egyptian girl. Tell all.
这个嘛 她全身光溜溜地
Well, she was naked
祭司们甚至还没离开房间呢
before the priests had left the room.
我不得不喊我的人进来把她从我身上拉下去
I had to call my people to pull her off me.
说真的
Seriously.
她正在悼念亡者
She was in mourning.
庄重而肃穆
She was very gray and formal.
她看上去像只小耗子
She was quite the little mouse.
以朱庇特的名义起誓？
On Jupiter's stone?
用他老婆的那玩意起誓
On Juno's cunt.
唉 没有 没发生什么有趣的事
Nothing at all interesting happened.
啊 她倒确实要求我正式承认
Oh, she did ask me to formally recognize
她的小崽子是恺撒的儿子
her bastard as Caesar's son.
真够无耻的
Blasted impudence!
你肯定拒绝了 对吧？
You refused, of course.
屋大维才是唯一…
Octavian is the only...
是的 是的 我当然拒绝了
Yes, yes, of course I refused.
结果女王陛下的眼泪
Which set off a great flood
都快要把我淹没了
of royal whining.
不 真是狗屎般的一天 到处都是
No, it's been a pig of a day all around.
统治这个城市根本不像我当初以为的那样有趣
Running this damn city isn't nearly as amusing as I thought it would be.
- 嗯 可怜的小羊羔 - 啊 天哪
- Poor lamb. - God
毫无疑问
More tedium to follow
明天的晚宴还有更多闷死人的东西
at this damn dinner tomorrow, no doubt.
赛维莉娅会来吗？
Is Servilia coming, by any chance?
是的
Yes.
很好 好极了
Good.
你有没有被一只海鳗咬过？
Have you ever been bitten by a moray eel?
我想是没有
I should think not.
你妈妈在哪儿？
Where's your mother?
- 有什么事不对吗？- 很有可能
- Something wrong? - Possibly.
啊 老天爷啊 她来这儿干什么？
Juno's mercy. What's she doing here?
我猜安东尼需要表现出团结
I suppose Antony wants a show of unity
给那些埃及人看
for the Egyptians.
我亲爱的赛维莉娅 你能来真是太好了
Servilia, my love, it's good of you to come.
我是强烈反对来这儿的 马克·安东尼坚持这么做
I am here under protest. Mark Antony's insistence.
他总是那么欺负人 不是吗？
He's a terrible bully, isn't he?
你一定是吓坏了
You must be very scared.
一点也不
Not in the slightest.
不过 你可不用怕我
Well, you need have no fear of me.
我可不想伤害你 真的
I wish you no harm, truly.
知道我已经赢了而你被踩在脚下 这就已经足够了
It's enough for me to know that I have won and you've been humbled.
我们都已经经历得够多的了
We've both suffered enough.
你在嘲讽我 我想是的
You are mocking me, I believe.
完全不是 我向你提供的可是友谊
Not at all. I'm offering you friendship
还有和解
and reconciliation.
你怎么说？
What do you say?
两个老朋友再回到一起
Two friends together?
在道义上我怎么能拒绝呢？
I cannot honorably refuse.
我还真是高兴啊
I'm so happy.
吻我一下 亲爱的
Kiss me, my dear.
享受这个晚宴吧
Enjoy the party.
你看到她脸上的表情了？真是千金难买
Did you see the look on her face? Priceless.
我看见泰门和他的人守在院子里
Mother, I saw Timon and some of his men in the yard.
一群刀斧手
Knife-and-hatchet men.
- 然后呢？- 我在想他们来这儿干什么？
- So? - I was wondering what they're doing here.
保安啰 还能有什么？
Security, what else?
最明显的目的不外乎绑架或是杀掉赛维莉娅
Their obvious purpose would be the abduction and killing of Servilia
- 只等她今晚离开时动手 - 真是胡说八道
- as she leaves this evening. - That's absurd.
祭司们可是都认可了停火的
There's a truce ratified by priests.
- 你不可以伤害她 - 停火？祭司？
- You can't harm her. - A truce? Priests?
你认为那条母狗会放在眼里吗？
You think that bitch cares?
现在有太多事情比你复仇的渴望还要危险
Mother, there is more at stake here than your desire for vengeance.
政治局势非常敏感
The political situation is extremely delicate.
她的死会把共和国再次推向骚乱的
Her death would throw the Republic into uproar.
- 我可管不着 - 你真是孩子气
- I don't care. - You're being childish.
安东尼知道这事吗？
Does Antony know of this?
他当然知道
Of course he does.
好吧 他不知道 这很明显 还有 你可不要去告诉他
All right, he doesn't, obviously. And don't you dare tell him.
对不起了 妈妈
I'm sorry, mother.
你这个小混蛋
You little bastard.
我不需要你了 你现在可以走了
I won't be needing you. You can go now.
你那些该死的埃及人在哪儿？都该上菜了
Where is your damned Egyptian? It's time to serve dinner.
我真想宣布全部这些都取消
I have a good mind to cancel the whole damn thing.
喔 别生气 你知道这样是不对的
Don't sulk, you know you're in the wrong.
跟你形容的一样
Just as you described her.
真是只小耗子
Quite the little mouse.
克莉奥佩特拉·菲洛帕特
Cleopatra Philopator,
莎草与蜂蜜之女主人
mistress of sedge and bee,
上下埃及的女王
queen of both upper and lower kingdoms.
拜托
Please...
我们该更随意些
We shall be informal.
我们该表现得好像彼此平等一样
We shall act as if we were all equals.
那样更有乐趣 你不认为吗？
It's much more fun that way, don't you think?
现在 给我介绍一下这些可爱的人
Now, who are all these lovely people?
啊…我们的女主人
Our hostess,
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii.
你好 阿提娅
Atia.
陛下您好
Your Highness.
很不错
Nice...
跟你说的一样
just as you said.
过来 孩子
Come here, boy.
这是我可爱的小凯撒
This is my darling Caesarion.
难道他看上去不是 跟他尊贵的父亲一模一样吗？
Does he not look exactly like his noble father?
真不可思议
Uncanny.
一点也不像他
Looks nothing like him.
我们可以用餐了吗？
Shall we eat?
你回来了 我还以为你会晚一点
You're back. I thought you'd be late.
- 我这不是回来了嘛 - 你肯定猜不到…
- Here I am. - You'll never guess...
- 泰维亚 - 里维埃？
- Tevye! - Levi?
孩子们 放开我 让我拥抱你们的父亲
Release me now, children. Let me hug your father.
你怎么来这儿了？
Why are you here?
真高兴看到你 兄弟
So happy to see your brother.
只要通知我一声就足够了
You gave me a start, that's all.
见到你真高兴 你该写封信来
I'm very happy to see you. You could've written.
哦 原谅我
Forgive me.
等到潮水一改变 我就跳上了一艘船 于是我就来了
I caught a ship on the tide's turn. Here I am.
看看你 都过了多长时间了 有八年了吧？
Look at you! How long's it been? Eight years?
九年 什么风把你吹来了？
Nine. What brings you here?
哦 我跟我的合伙人打算 在这儿开始一点小生意
My partners and I are setting up a new business.
我打算在这儿开个办事处
I'm to run the office here.
- 就是说你会在这里待上一阵子啰？- 如果你不反对的话
- You'll be staying a while, then? - If you'll have me.
当然不 我们的家就是你的家
Of course. Our house is your house.
你怎么没给他做晚饭？
Why haven't you made him dinner?
不 没关系 我不饿
No, that's all right. I'm not hungry.
我们不是犹太人
We're not kosher.
看来我们这儿还不够好 是吧
Already we're not good enough?
- 嗯 至少来点酒吧 - 还用你说
- Well, have some wine at least. - Now you're talking.
这么说你还在买卖香料了？
So, you're still in spices?
香料 布料 油 谢谢
Spices, cloth, oil. Thank you.
- 生意还好吧？- 时好时坏的
- Goes well, I hope? - Oh, up, down, up, down.
就这样了
It goes.
你呢 黛博拉告诉我你混得不错
And you? Deborah tells me you're doing very well.
时好 时坏
Oh, up, down.
卖马？
Horses?
马
Horses.
再见 执政官
Consul, farewell.
你忠诚的女王将以泪洗面
Your vassal queen shall weep
直到再一次见到你为止
till she sees you again.
我也希望不久能够再见
I shall see you soon, then, I hope.
阿提娅
Atia,
我们将成为终身的挚友
I have made a friend for life.
我能感觉到
I feel it.
确实
Indeed.
吻我
Kiss me.
去死吧 猪养的荡妇
Die screaming, you pig-spawn trollop.
一路顺风 女王陛下
Safe journey, Your Highness.
终于结束了
Well, I'm glad that's...
晚会结束 全部回家去
Party's over! Everybody can go home now!
实话告诉我
So tell me the truth now.
你来这儿干嘛？
Why are you here?
我说了 做生意
I told you, I'm just setting up a new business.
你恨罗马 恨罗马人
You hate Rome. You hate Romans.
你不止一次说过他们都是人渣
How many times did you tell me what scum they are?
卑鄙的暴徒 巴比伦的贱货
Vile oppressors, Babylonian whores.
你会想住在他们中间？我觉得不可能
And now you've come to live amongst them. I don't think so.
生意归生意 我是来赚钱的
Business is business. This is where the money is.
我在耶路撒冷那儿有点小麻烦
Things were getting a little hot for me in Jerusalem.
最好离开一阵子
Better I leave for a while.
- 麻烦？什么麻烦？- 政治的
- Things? What things? - Politics.
没什么要紧的
Nothing serious.
也许我言论过于自由了点
Maybe I spoke a little too freely.
- 哦 兄弟 - 作为一个人 我怎么能保持沉默呢？
- Oh, brother. - How is a man to stay silent?
我们所谓的领袖们在舔罗马士兵的靴子
Our so-called leaders lick the boots of Roman soldiers.
- 法利赛人 - 听着
- The Pharisees are... - You listen to me.
你现在是在罗马 在我家里 我得为我妻子和孩子们设想
You're in Rome now. In my house. I've a wife and children to think of.
你可以高谈阔论但不要在这儿 听懂了吗？
You keep that cack to yourself. Do you hear me?
听懂了
I hear you.
那好
All right, then.
按住了
Hold him down.
拖出来
Take him out.
他死了
He's dead.
帮我个小忙好吗？
Would you do me a small favor?
回去告诉我的朋友
Go back and tell my friend
我已经不想和他讲道理了
that I have given up trying to reason with him.
在冥后珀耳塞福涅威严的橡树之上 艾文台山的一切
Everything on the Aventine above Persephone's Oak
都是我的领地
is my territory now.
如果他再敢动我的人
If he touches any man of mine again,
把我惹恼了他麻烦就大了 如果我真的…
there's a grave danger that I will become irate, and if I do...
所有公会长和公会人员注意
Captains and men of the collegia.
以和平之母之名
Under the auspices of Mother Concord,
以神圣之名我宣布停战
a sanctified truce is declared.
满月之前不应再有暴力
Violence shall cease until the waxing of the moon.
六点钟
At the sixth hour
召集所有公会长
all captains are summoned
参加和谈
to attend a parley
地点是艾文台公会
at the Aventine collegium.
这他妈怎么回事？
What the fuck's all this, then?
- 不知道 - 谁召集和谈？
- I don't know. - Who called a parley?
- 没人知道 - 祭司一定知道
- Nobody knows. - The priest must know.
你不能与和平祭司说话
You can't talk to a priest of Concord.
- 为什么？- 就是不能 你这个愚蠢的野蛮人
- Why not? - Because you can't, you fucking savage.
外邦人
Foreigners.
发生什么事了？
What's going on?
我叫卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
My name is Lucius Vorenus.
经罗马执政官马克·安东尼的授权
I speak to you under the authorization
我召集你们开会
of Mark Antony, Consul of Rome.
公会长们 跟我进来
Captains, follow me.
你们将听到的话会对你们有好处
You'll hear something to your benefit.
那就过来吧
Come on, then.
执政官马克·安东尼宣布
Consul Mark Antony declares your contest
你们为取得艾文台山的控制权 而进行的争战到此为止
for control of the Aventine is finished.
- 所有暴乱必须停止 - 随他怎么宣布
- All violence will cease. - He can declare what he likes.
要我们停止想也别想
It doesn't make it so.
作为杀死伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼的人
As killer of Erastes Fulmen,
我宣布他所执掌的艾文台公会
I claim his captaincy of the Aventine collegium
也由我管理
as my rightful spoils.
艾文台是我的了
The Aventine is now mine.
- 你没权利这么做 - 我已经做了
- You can't do that. - Yet here I am.
你可以占着这个老痞子的窝不走 但是你手下没有人
You can have this old rat's nest if you like, but you've got no men.
你的人不是死了就是逃了
They're all dead or run away.
人我会再找
I'll find men.
罗马不缺暴徒
Rome has no shortage of criminal scum.
也许我还会从你们那儿挖点过来
Maybe I'll take some of yours.
兄弟们 当纪念和平之母
Brothers, remember the lady.
我们都了解你卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
We all know of you, Lucius Vorenus.
我们知道你是个正派人 我们对你也相当尊重
We know you're a man of gravity and we're duly respectful.
对于我们的尊重你该知恩图报
You would do well to return that respect.
这我不能 但我可以给你们钱作为补偿
I can't do that, but I can give you coin instead.
一旦社会秩序恢复
Once order is restored,
所有公会每个月将领到5000德那留斯银币
all collegia will receive a monthly stipend of 5,000 denarii
钱直接由执政官马克·安东尼拨发 由我管理
directly from Consul Mark Antony under my supervision.
作为回报
In return,
他希望你们停手 恢复你们独立自主互不干涉的传统
he expects you will limit yourself to your traditional liberties and malpractices.
不允许再有影响贸易正常 和政治稳定的事发生
Nothing that will disrupt trade or politics.
还有什么？
Anything else?
当然了 如果城内发生暴动
Naturally, should there be civil violence,
你们和你们的人将被召集
you and your people will be called upon
站在执政官一边维护他的权益
to defend the rights of the Consul.
我希望你们好好想想
I require your acknowledgement
接受这些条款
and acceptance of these terms.
5000德那留斯银币…
5,000 denarii...
不错
that's not bad.
现金还是粮食？
In cash or grain?
- 随你们 - 你是个女人吗？
- As you like. - Are you women?
这条走狗只吠了一声 你们就乖乖屈膝了
One bark from this red dog and you bend your neck.
你叫什么？
What's your name?
盖乌斯·伊格纳斯·阿塞伯
Gaius Ignus Acerbo,
俄比安公会长
Captain of the Oppian Colleges.
告诉我们 为什么像我们这样理智 受人尊敬的人
Tell us, why would sane and respectable men like ourselves
要和你这样摇尾乞怜的受诅咒的野兽做这笔交易？
do business with a poor, cursed, hounded beast like you?
盖乌斯·伊格纳斯·阿塞伯
Gaius Ignus Acerbo,
问得好
you ask a fair question.
不接受协议的人将是我的敌人
Those of you who will not do business with me are my enemy.
他们很快会死
And so?
比想象的还快
They will die much sooner than they expect.
注意 当纪念和平之母
Steady on. Remember blessed Concord.
不许动手
No menaces.
和平之母
Concord.
我是冥神之子
I am a son of Hades!
操他妈的和平之母
I fuck Concord in her arse!
- 协议成立 - 兄弟
- The truce is raised! - Brother!
阿塞伯 你接受吗？
Acerbo, will you do business with me?
- 对 很有趣 对吧？- 我警告你 女人
- Yes, it's funny, isn't it? - I warn you, woman,
再说我和那个贱女人一个字 我就…
another word about that damn girl and I will...
你就怎么样？
You will what? What will you do?
又要吵了？
Fighting again?
你们累不累
How tiresome.
我没碰过那个女人
I never touched that woman!
你就说你的吧
So you keep saying.
- 早上好 - 早上好
- Good morning. - Good morning.
好吧 安东尼 关于我的钱
Antony, about my money...
哦 上帝怜悯我们 我…
Oh, gods beneath us. I...
- 现在不是时候 屋大维 - 事情到底有进展没有？
- Not now, Octavian. - Has the matter moved forward at all?
告诉我 孩子 如果我真的把钱给你
Tell me, boy, if I did give you the money,
你到底他妈的想干什么？
what on Gaia's great arse would you do with it?
这个问题回答起来很复杂
That's a complex question,
但我首先要把钱分给群众 那是凯撒答应他们的
but I'd certainly start by giving the plebs the money that Caesar promised them.
那你就太蠢了
Then you're a fool.
最基本的政治原则 年轻人
Basic politics, lad.
他们拿了钱一旦都花光了
Once they have the money and spend it,
他们就会想要更多
then they will want more money.
到时候你要怎么办？
And what are you gonna do then?
如果你仍然坚持这个态度 我恐怕要请一个律师了
I was afraid you'd take this attitude, so I've engaged a lawyer.
一个律师
A lawyer.
他会帮助伯斯卡尽快把钱转移到我名下
He can help Posca expedite the delay in transferring the money to me.
你在想什么？我们和安东尼是一家人
What were you thinking? Antony's family.
事实上他不是
He's not, actually.
好吧 孩子
All right, boy,
你可以告诉你的律师
you can tell your lawyer
让他用蜡烛戳自己的屁眼
to shove a taper up his arse
再坐下来
and set himself alight.
你一个子儿也别想拿到
You'll not get one brass obol of that money.
一分没有
Nothing.
别这样 亲爱的
Come on, my love.
弟弟 把水果色拉递给我好吗？
Brother, will you pass the fruit salad?
看看你都干了什么？
See what you've done?
很抱歉如果我让你的爱人不高兴了
I'm sorry if I've disturbed your love affair.
- 我只是… - 哦 闭嘴 傻瓜
- I merely... - Oh, shut up, you fool.
去他妈的爱吧
Love affair be damned.
你必须去道歉并保证不再提钱的事了
You will apologize and promise to stop all this talk about money.
去告诉他你很高兴 他能够管理凯撒的财产
Tell him that you're perfectly happy for him to administer Caesar's estate.
- 但我不高兴 - 你以为我高兴吗？
- But I'm not happy. - Do you think I am?
我们还有别的选择吗？
What choice do we have?
你不觉得我们现在得依靠安东尼吗？
Don't you see we're dependent on Antony now?
如果你把他赶走了谁来保护我们？谁？
Who will protect us if you drive him away from me? Who?
- 我完全有能力保护你们 - 哦 别说了
- I'm perfectly capable. - Please don't.
马克·安东尼不费吹灰之力 就能灭了你这样的小鬼
Mark Antony buggers boys like you for a morning snack.
你去道歉 就这么定了
You will apologize, and there's an end on it.
色拉里没无花果了
There's not enough figs in this salad.
嘿 嘿
Hei, Hei
够了
That's enough!
滚 滚
Vai. Vai!
走开 滚
Off with you! Vai!
谢谢您 大人
Thank you, sir.
求您了大人 我需要工作
Please, sir, I need work.
我什么都能做
I'll do anything.
我能做你的性奴
I'll suck your cock.
你为什么老要为那笔钱的事找麻烦？
Why are you making all this fuss over the money?
很明显他永远不会给你的
It was obvious he'd never give it to you.
你这样只会让母亲操心
All you're doing is making Mother anxious.
姐姐
Sister,
你必须发誓我告诉你的事 你不会让任何人知道
you must promise me never to speak of what I tell you now.
哦 上帝
Oh, gods.
我发誓
I promise.
共和国已经在灭亡的边缘了
The Republic is on the brink of an abyss.
安东尼… 安东尼是个野兽
Antony... Antony's a destructive brute.
元老院的那帮人胆小懦弱
The Senate is weak and cowardly,
群众因欲望和愤怒不断生事
and the plebs are roiling in want and anger.
罗马需要新的领袖
Rome is in need of new leadership.
我能担起这个责任
I can provide that leadership.
如今我已经想好几个措施了
Now, I already have several initiatives un...
这没好处 说什么冥王之子
It'll come to no good, this Hades business.
但是奏效了不是吗？那混蛋妥协了
Worked though, didn't it? The bastards fell into line.
你确实把他娘的吓倒了
You scared the fuck out of them right enough,
但我说的不是这个
but that's not the point.
你不是什么冥王之子 你是个高尚的人
You're no son of Hades. You're a mortal man.
上帝不会喜欢从高尚的人口中 听到这种屁话
The gods don't like this sort of shit from mortal men.
我只是在完成罗马执政官交给我的任务
I'm following the orders of a consul of Rome, my master by oath,
这么做是为了恢复和平和社会秩序 这对共和国有好处
for the sake of peace and public order, for the good of the Republic.
你跟我还是不跟？
Are you with me or not?
我跟你
I'm with you.
朱庇特神的光辉照耀 盖乌斯·屋大维·凯撒
By grace of Jupiter, Gaius Octavian Caesar,
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒的合法继承人
lawful son of Gaius Julius Caesar,
庄严承诺
makes this his pledge
他个人将履行他慈爱父亲的遗嘱
that he personally will fulfill the terms
将遗产的一部分分发给人民
of his beloved father's bequest to the people.
三月份接下去的9天里
In the fields of Mars next nine days,
所有合法公民和士兵
all eligible citizens and soldiers
每人将领到300青铜币) (1德那留斯银币=4青铜币)
will receive 300 sestertii
钱直接来自盖乌斯·屋大维
from the hands of Octavian Caesar himself!
我宣布 凯撒的儿子
Let it be known that Caesar's son has sold away
将变卖他所有的个人财产
all his own property
来履行他父亲的遗愿
to honor his father's wishes.
愿他的虔诚得到上帝的祝福
May such piety bring blessings upon him.
- 你都干了什么？- 起来
- What have you done? - Wake up!
马上起来
Wake up at once!
你这是什么意思？
What is the meaning of this?
- 什么？- 钱
- What? - The money!
你把钱分了
You're giving the plebs their money!
已经这么晚了吗？
Is it so late already?
我睡过头了
I've overslept.
我不在乎 钱是怎么回事？
I don't care. What about the money?
我承诺过的
I've promised it.
抱歉我之前没有告诉你
I'm sorry I didn't tell you before now.
我知道你会反对
But I knew you'd object.
我决定涉政了
I've decided to enter public life.
这似乎是让民众认识我的最佳方法
This seemed the best way to introduce myself to the people.
我会把这认为 是对我直接的挑衅
That will be seen as a direct challenge to me.
我知道 但我根本没有这么想
Yes, but that isn't my intention at all.
我建议我们一起做一场公众演讲 表现我们的团结
I suggest we make a public display of unity to quash such notions.
公众演讲表现我们的团结？
A public display of unity!
这很有意义 我们的利益是息息相关的
It makes sense. Our interests are conjoined.
在你的执政期 我得到的名誉等于是你的
While you are consul, my name will lend weight to yours.
当你的执政期结束时
And when your consulship is over,
你如你所承诺的一样退出政治舞台
and you retire from politics as you have promised,
我能接替你继续领导凯撒的集团
I will step in as leader of the Caesarian party.
我懂了
I see.
到时候你在元老院里惹的那些仇家 如果找麻烦
You will need protection from your enemies in the Senate,
我能保护你
and I can provide that.
你他妈的以为你是什么东西？
Just who the fuck do you think you are?
- 我是凯撒的合法继承人 - 不要 冷静点
- I'm Caesar's rightful heir. - Now just stay calm.
他没拿到钱 所以他不可能发放不是吗？
He doesn't have the money, so he can't give it away, can he?
这只是小孩子说戏话
This is all just childish talk.
我是那笔钱的合法拥有者
The money is legally mine.
我可以抵押借贷
I was able to borrow against it.
- 借？- 借？
- Borrow? - Borrow?
你借了多少？
How much did you borrow?
和我计划的比起来不算多少
It's not so much in the great scheme of things.
多少？
How much?
300万青铜币
Three million sestertii.
哦 见鬼
Juno's cunt!
你这个傻瓜 愚蠢的孩子
You stupid, stupid boy!
你…
You...
你这个蠢货
You stupid little shit!
荡妇
Fucking whore!
道歉 道歉
Apologize! Apologize.
好了 别管他了
That's it, now. Just leave it now.
- 道歉 - 不
- Apologize! - No!
不 够了
No, enough.
小杂种
Little fuck.
安东尼
Antony!
住手
Stop it!
安东尼 让他去吧
Antony, leave him!
别管他 别管他 看着我
Leave him. Leave him. Leave him. Look at me!
看着我 看着我
Look at me! Look at me!
放手
Stop it!
Stop it.
朱诺神啊
Juno's mercy!
你们怎么了？
What's the matter with you?
你活着算你走运
You're lucky you're breathing!
- 你听到没有？- 走吧
- Do you hear me, boy? - Come on.
- 活着算你走运 - 野兽
- You're lucky you're breathing! - Animal!
你没资格领导罗马
You're not fit to lead Rome!
那么你是谁？
Who are you, then?
妓院的奴隶 服侍三个老鸨
Slave of the college brothel over by three bells.
抱歉 宝贝 我们不需要妓女了
Sorry, love, we've plenty of whores.
我不是
No, I'm no whore.
你要我猜？
You gonna make me guess?
我管她们 维持嫖客之间的秩序
Supervisor. I handle the girls, keep the customers in line.
叫什么？
Name?
罗马人叫我盖娅
Romans call me Gaia.
你的人叫你什么？
What do your own people call you?
- 不关你的事 - 很公平
- Not your business. - Fair enough.
我要单人房间 我想吃什么就吃什么
I get my own room, I eat what I want.
妓院每收入500个钱币 我要得一个提成
Every 500 coins that comes through the brothel, I get one.
- 存起来赎身是吧？- 不
- Saving up to buy your freedom, are you? - No.
买一件毛皮大衣
A fur coat.
录用她
Sign her up.
谢了 老板
Thanks, boss.
马修斯兄弟
Brother Mascius.
波罗 你这浑球
Pullo, you black dog.
你还活着？
You're still alive?
你是来入伙的？
You've come to join up, then?
听说你们在招兵买马
I heard you were hiring.
我还以为你过得不错 种田什么的
Oh, I thought you were well set, farm and all.
我种够了
Oh, crooked dice done for that.
- 可惜 - 还能怎么样
- Shame. - What can you do?
总不会再种田吧
Didn't like farming much anyway.
你确定吗 兄弟 这条路可不好走啊
Be sure about this, brother. It's a dark road we're on.
没人知道路通往哪里
No one knows where it will lead.
条条大路通罗马 不是吗？
All roads lead to the same place, don't they?
没错
That they do.
很高兴你加入我们
Glad to have you with us.
到后面来和乌瑞纳斯打个招呼
Come through the back and say hello to Vorenus,
- 让老混蛋高兴高兴 - 他们说的都是真的吗？
- cheer up the old bastard. - Is it true what they say?
- 关于他妻子和孩子的事？- 都是真的
- About the wife and children? - True enough.
一句也别提
Not a fucking word.
- 乌瑞纳斯兄弟 - 马修斯 你好吗？
- Brother Vorenus. - Mascius, how are you?
我还行 还行
I'm fair. Fair.
他要入伙
Come to join our merry band.
你提醒过他了 对吧？
You tried to warn him off, did you?
对
I did.
这可不是军队 兄弟
This isn't the army, brother.
我们是和拉皮条的
We here, we're pimps,
杀手 小偷混在一起
knifemen, thieves.
你确定你要堕落成这样吗？
Are you sure you've sunk so low?
我从卡普阿一路过来 睡在田沟里
I walked here from Capua. I slept in ditches.
我到了这儿 就听到人们在议论
When I get here, I hear people talking.
他们说一个黑心的恶棍
They say a black-hearted villain
占了艾文台公会
has taken over the Aventine college.
他们说他和死神是一伙的
He's in league with the gods below, they say.
他的名字叫卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
And his name is Lucius Vorenus.
我心想:马修斯 老家伙
Well, I thought to myself, "Mascius, old boy,
你转运了
"your luck has changed."
看到没有 波罗 我说了我了解自己
See, Pullo, I told you I know what I'm about.
那不对 上帝不会喜欢
It's not right. The gods don't like it.
对啊
Yeah.
上帝还能拿我怎么办？
What more can the gods do to me?
现在他们要怎么惩罚我？
How can they punish me now?
不知道
Don't know.
也不想知道
Don't wanna find out.
你听说这个好消息了吗？
Have you heard the good news?
是的
I have.
这是他们倒台的开始
This is the beginning of the end for them.
毫无疑问
From your lips to the ears of the gods.
安东尼这样的蠢货注定要失败
A fool like Antony was sure to blunder.
他们只会窝里斗
They'll fight among themselves and destroy each other.
我怀疑那孩子比安东尼好不了多少
I doubt the boy will be more than a nuisance to Antony.
他还不够和安东尼斗
He cannot hope to rival him.
凯撒可不是心血来潮选中这个孩子
Caesar did not choose the boy on a whim.
- 他会让你大吃一惊的 - 但愿
- He'll surprise you, I think. - We can hope.
元老院该召我儿子回来了
The Senate should ask my son to return.
是时候了
The time is ripe.
让布鲁图斯回来？
Brutus return?
不
No.
还不行 还不是时候 我认为
Not yet. Not quite yet, I think.
那什么时候？
When?
我们必须等着看事态的进一步发展
We must wait and see how things develop.
等等看？
Wait and see?
非凡的战略
A noble strategy.
不非凡 但至少 合理
Not noble, perhaps, but sensible.
不管怎么说 告诉你儿子 我…
In any case, tell your son that I...
不 不是我
No, not I...
是他在罗马的朋友们
His friends in Rome
都期盼着能再见到他
look forward to seeing him again
在不久将来的某个时候
at some point in the near future.
我会告诉他
I will tell him.
亲爱的母亲
"My dear mother,
我留下这封信向你道别
"I write to bid you farewell.
你那样对我我很难过
"I'm very sorry you chose to act as you did.
我希望你能够认识到 你犯的错误的严重后果
"I hope in time you will understand the gravity of your mistake.
我要你知道 我的心一如既往的坚定
"Be assured, I'm as determined as ever
我要追求我的政治生涯
"to pursue a political career.
别担心我的安全
"Do not be concerned for my safety.
我在去南部平原的路上
"I'm on the road south to Campania
到了那儿我会和我的朋友阿格里帕呆在一起 他在那儿很有权势
"where I'll stay with my friend Agrippa, who is well established there.
我仍是你谦恭的儿子 屋大维
"I remain your respectful son, Octavian."